if you dedicated the next year solely to
getting better at strong lifting you
would see much better changes to your
physique than you would with your
traditional bodybuilding or bikini
training now it is true strong lifting
is a strength program but it's more of a
physique program and the reason why is
most people don't understand progressive
overload they go to the gym they do the
same thing over and over they switch
things around too much and they never
get good at anything they're not placing
increasing amounts of tension on the
muscles you can hit each muscle from
every angle and utilize the mind muscle
connection and get a pump and feel the
burn you can sweat you can be sore those
things don't guarantee marked increases
in muscle mass getting stronger at the
most important big basic compound
movements almost always guarantees a
better physique so i'm not saying that
every bodybuilder is doing it wrong you
know every bikini competitor is doing it
wrong the top people have the methods
that work for them but all these people
down here the masses they should be
doing strong lifting you need to get
really good at squats really good at
deadlifts great at hip thrusts good at
bench pressing good at military pressing
you need to be able to bust out chin ups
if you're ever going to really develop
your physique and quite frankly most
people never take the time to do so they
don't put in the work they're constantly
distracted by new workouts new programs
new workouts from their favorite
influencers new burnouts new circuits
this booty band burnout you know the gym
got a new machine i'm gonna try that
it'll do anything but get better at the
big basics all right what is strongaging
so first off i'm going to tell you how
it all came to be then i'll go over the
rationale and rules then i'm going to
discuss some of the benefits and
influences finally i'll discuss the
future of strong lifting
[Music]
what is strong lifting take one
so how it all came to be so when the
pandemic started i started training my
client allegra like every single day and
we quickly developed a program which
came to be known as the allegra pr plan
now you can check out allegra's physique
results they're amazing as you can see
but what you don't see is her crazy
strength gains and i was pushing her so
hard we were doing squats we were doing
deadlifts we were doing hip thrusts at
first
she fought me on training her upper body
but over time then she started pushing
pr's on bench press and military press
and chin-ups now that's not to say we
didn't do other lifts we do all the
lists we love all the lifts i love all
the lifts i'm a biomechanist i'm a
lifter for 30 years i'm a bodybuilder at
heart i love every exercise but some
movements are more important than others
and so they should be prioritized in
training so with allegra she wanted to
train glutes every single day so it's
okay we're going to have our squat day
and on her squat day she's also going to
do 45 degree hypers and some glutes then
she's going to have her hip thrust day
she has her deadlift day and on the
daily day she does a single leg
squatting movement like a a long durable
guarantee squatter step up and finishes
off with some glutes and then she has
her heavy hip thrust day where she does
heavy hip thrust and then lockout work
for the hip just and then some abduction
work and more glute work then i try to
get her to do upper body and then she'd
cycle back around so because of the
frequency i couldn't give her too much
volume on any given day especially given
the fact that we were going high effort
we're going for prs when you're hitting
pr's and training frequently you can't
bust out five sets to failure you know
you can't recover in time so what we
would do is we would warm up i'd watch
your squat for example i'd see how 135
moved and i'd look at 185 those were her
indicator sets all right if they moved
quickly i'd say wow you look strong
today i'd go you want to go for a new
one rep max you want to hit a heavy pr
and she'd say yeah brett you know 185
felt so light or she'd say i want to see
if i can hit 205 for five and she said
you know let's go for a new one rep max
you know let's see if we can hit 230. or
she'd say i don't know that kind of felt
slow i kind of feel drained today maybe
we go for a record with 185 and on the
day she really didn't look good the days
were 135 and 185 moved real slowly then
i'd say all right let's just hit a pr
with 135. you haven't done that in a
long time that'll be easy for you you
know maybe she hit 15 reps the last time
she did 135 pound squats well she's
gained a lot of strength since then she
can easily hit 135 for 16 or 17 or 18
even though she's not feeling up for it
that day so we kind of saved the high
rapiers for days she wasn't feeling that
good so she'd still hit a pr and still
feel productive it was good for the
psyche then the next day all right warms
up on the deadlift all right if it look
if things look crisp if things look
snappy let's go for a pr i knew all of
her pr's at every different load i knew
for example with deadlifts i knew the
exact number of reps she had gotten with
185 you know 205 225 245 i knew her one
rep max i know i remember the first time
she hit 225 then her one rep max was 260
for a while then it was 265 then
eventually she hit 275 and with hip
thrust she was always such a great hip
thruster during that first year the
pandemic went from 500 to 600 pounds you
know she put 100 pounds on her hip
thrust and she hit 600 pounds when she
only weighed 125. you know that's 4.8
times body weight so yeah she could work
her way up to a five times body weight
hip thrust and look at her glutes look
at how her glutes change along the way
so she made that connection when i hit
pr's my physique improves and i got her
in that mindset and i got her involved
in the process you want the lifter you
want the athlete giving their input you
want them involved in the decision
making you want them to say all right i
feel like hitting this pr today i want
to go for this load so you've got all
these different loads on all the
different lifts and those are all pr
opportunities and she was seeing such
crazy results that a lot of my squad
members were saying hey what's allegra
doing you know i want in on it i said
well we're doing
we wrote a special plan you want in i'll
i'll give you the same program so
eventually almost all the squad members
at one point were doing the allegra pr
plan and their strength just starts
skyrocketing you know oh i said i'm
looking around i'm like man i have a
strong squad they're turning into a
bunch of freaks well one day my client
carly he's hip thrust in 700 plus pounds
and there's another lady across the
country you know in miami by the name of
katie sonier and she's also hypnotizing
700 plus pounds you know so
i had this idea i want to see who's the
strongest hip thruster between carly
petritis and katie sonier now that never
happened but that's what sparked the
idea because the more i thought about
i'm like katie's got a couple of coaches
who are hip-thrusting a ton of weight
too i've got a lot of girls who are
hip-thrusting freaks what if we did a
big hip thrust off and then i thought
about i'm like well why just hip-thrust
why not do a full-on strength
competition and then i start thinking
you know i've always loved powerlifting
i love squats i love bench i love
deadlifts but i never thought
powerlifting is a complete package when
it comes to the physique you're lacking
in some areas if you're a powerlifter
you're probably going to develop decent
pecs and front delts and triceps from
all the bench pressing you know you're
probably going to get big quads from all
the squatting you know your hammies
might be well developed because of the
deadlifting you'd think that power
lifters would have amazing glutes
because they're squatting and dead
lifting but if you've ever been to a
local meet you know i've been to dozens
of local powerlifting meets and they're
wearing singlets you know you can't hide
your glute development i'm actually
amazed a lot at the lack of glute
development with powerlifters who are
squatting and deadlifting all the time
so i think you know you're missing some
opportunity in the glutes you're missing
some in the lats you know yes they'll do
their rows and pull downs but they don't
prioritize chin ups for example they
don't they might do military press as an
accessory for bench press but they don't
prioritize it like they prioritize the
bench press so powerlifting is brutal
it's really hard because it's it's so
challenging to get good at three
exercises especially given that squats
and deadlifts kind of compete with one
another you know you hammer deadlifts
you usually need a couple days off
before you squat because your low back
might be fatigued you know i start
thinking about i'm like you know i love
i love squats i love bench i love
deadlifts but i also love three other
lifts you know i love chin ups i love
military press and i love hip thrust so
this goes into the rationale behind the
program you think well why just these
six lifts they all lend themselves well
to one rep maxes you know i also love
rose those are a medium to high rep
range exercise you try a one rep max row
you know even like seal rows are popular
uh in australia for example in new
zealand everyone does steroids you go
heavy on them and you start flailing
around you look like a seal you know
your low back arches your feet start
moving around you do a heavy bent over
row or a cedar row you're gonna use a
ton of momentum and then it's not even
more of a full body lift doesn't really
measure your lat strength because you're
just using tons of momentum there's a
lot of great glute exercise out there
but not many that land themselves well
to one rep maxes a one rep mac back
extension or a one rep max lunge or a
one rep max kickback i just don't see it
happening those exercises are better
suited for medium to high wraps so this
six lifts make a lot of sense when you
start thinking about well they are very
conducive to one rep maxes but they
combine to maximally build the physique
no stone gets left unturned military
press is gonna develop your shoulders
bench press is gonna develop your pecs
chin ups are gonna develop your lats
bench and military are gonna develop
your triceps chin ups are gonna develop
your biceps abs are made in the kitchen
chin ups work the abs really well
contrary to what most people think
chin-ups are actually one of the best ab
exercises there are squats annihilate
the quads deadlifts work the hammies hip
thrusts hammer the glutes but squats and
deads help build the glutes as well and
squats tend to develop the calves as
well the bottom line all the muscles get
worked with strong lifting and you can't
say that with any other strength sport
with every other strength sport you're
leaving some room on the table so is
strong lifting a strength or a physique
program well the answer is both i use
strength training to build my physique i
love getting stronger i stay awake at
night thinking of how i can get stronger
at the main lift so what strategy i can
use you know i'm always trying to find
the right assistance lift so the
combination of frequency intensity and
effort it's going to maximize my results
on this certain lift i'm always trying
new variations i'm always trying new
programs to try to maximize my strength
and i'm 45 and i'm still set in pr's 30
years of lifting i'm still building
strength i'm still building muscle but
you can be the judge yourself in the
year that i developed strong lifting i
have never seen anywhere close to that
crazy of results with my clientele and
here i'll show off some of my clients
you know i could roll through a bunch of
the clients but i think the best case
study the best anecdote is ashley hodge
ashley hodge poured herself into strong
lifting and here's what's crazy i made a
post on recomping with ashley and i
talked about strength training is fat
loss training and i talked about
recomping since i made that post she's
further recomped if she keeps getting
smaller and smaller but she stays the
same way because she gets stronger and
stronger the stronger you get at any
given body weight the smaller you become
because at equal weights muscle takes up
less space than fat so as you're
recomping building muscle and losing fat
simultaneously you build muscle in the
right areas that make you look athletic
you lose fat from the areas that kind of
make you look less appealing the problem
areas so that changes your shape around
but you also get smaller overall and
look at ashley here in all these
pictures she weighs the same between
like 131 and like 134 so i've put all of
my clients on strong lifting programs
this year i mean you can check out
amanda here look at her recomping and
these are accompanied by
massive increases in strength look at
alexis you can check out gabby you can
look at brianna here you can look at
jackie here's alyssa this is lorita
chrissana tori all of these ladies
competed in bikini over the last six
months and what i like about bikini
competitions you get to see you know
you're on stage you get to see the
fruits of your labor did your physique
improve you know there's no hiding
whether it did or not so yes i train my
bikini competitors as strong lifters you
know they're doing this crazy strength
training programs and look at the
results i had five glute squad members
do their first show with wbff this year
all five of them won their pro cards in
their very first show they went five for
five five glue squad members all got
their pro cards their first show why is
that because we train so much harder
than the competition and you can see
that in their shape my girls glutes are
amazing but their backs are crazy too
and that's from the chin ups so with
bikini competitors i strongly believe
that after a competition they should
sign up for a strong lifting meet it
takes their mind off of physique
competitions and puts their mind onto
strength goals the next time they go on
stage their physique will improve
because they got stronger they built
muscle it sets you up for future success
just some of the basic rules with strong
lifting all right we have the same rules
for the three power lifts as
powerlifting does you know they did a
great job with squats you gotta drop
below parallel that's deeper than most
people think with bench press you need
to posit the chest for a second before
you lift the bar up that lifts you have
to lock it out you know you got to stand
tall and wait for the judge to tell you
it's good but with the three new lifts
you know military press and chin ups and
hip thrusts we had to come up with the
rules you know so with military you have
to start with the bar touching your
shoulders you know and you wait for the
command you have to fully lock it out
you can't lock it out here you have to
push your head through same with
chin-ups you start from a dead hang you
can't start here you have to start from
a fully stretched position and wait for
the command then you have to touch your
chest to the bar it's not just getting
your chin over the bar it's getting the
bar to touch your chest it's a lot
harder that way and hip thrusts you know
most people don't fully lock out their
hip thrust when they go heavy hip
thrusts you have to reach full hip
extension and you have to pause for a
brief moment and wait for the command so
these strong lifting meets they're so
much fun we've done four of them now the
first one was in miami in october of
2020. each meet we've learned a little
bit we've improved upon it the next meet
we did was in december of 2020 just over
a year ago today and that was in tulum
and then we ended up extending the trip
and going to cancun that was the best
week of my entire life there were over
30 of us who went to tulum for the sole
purpose of crushing it in the strong
lifting competition that day was magical
i will never forget it you know i had so
many of the girls like i just have these
memories etched in my head of you know
amanda and ashley hodge and angela hip
thrusting and jade but the craziest
memory from tulum was carly patridis you
know it was just you had to be there but
the hype was insane she was going for a
765 hip thrust and she hit it so 765 is
eight plates per side i don't think
people realize how freaking heavy that
is so she nailed 765 with excellent form
the crowd went wild everyone was
cheering like crazy and just to see the
the raw emotion come out of her it was
magical and uh that's when i started
realizing holy crap i have the strongest
female gym in the world of all natural
lifters they're all natural none of them
take steroids none of them take anything
they're all natural and they look and
feel amazing that's what i love about it
they're they're confident they're fun
and you know when they want to diet down
they can diet down and get ripped but
sometimes they want to eat a little bit
more they're fine with that too because
they know they're going to be large and
in charge they're going to gain shape in
all the right areas like i said my
girl's legs are amazing and when they
gain some weight they still look great
because they're getting so strong so you
have a lot of wiggle room when you're a
strong lifter you want to be a little
bit smaller you want to be a little bit
bigger they both have their pros and
cons but yeah we were eating a lot we
were eating like crazy back then
celebrating a lot going to dinners we're
having a lot of fun but then some of the
girls started dieting down and that's
when it was like whoa now you're seeing
the fruits of their labor you know i
remember saying to jade and amanda like
you girls look like you could step on
stage in like six weeks you haven't been
doing prep you're walking around you
know i've been training these girls for
four years i know what they look like
typically in the off season this is the
best they've ever looked by far during
the off season so if you're doing strong
lifting training and managing your
weight you don't have to do a 16 week
prep if you if you're a bikini
competitor you might only need six or
eight weeks you know and that's what i
like too i want people to look and feel
good 365 days a year so tulum was
amazing we went on to do a san diego
event this was in march of 2021 and this
event was awesome because i think there
were like six different girls who hit
600 plus pound hip thrusts and then we
did an la event in august of 2021 and
this one we opened it up to the public
and it was awesome because we made some
new friends there were a couple lifters
there that just blew us out of the water
these girls saw what i was doing and
they're like okay i want a piece of that
it's just so cool to to make new friends
and have this like-minded community so
training for a strong lifting like i
said power lifting is hard enough trying
to build three lists but strong lifting
you're trying to build
six different lifts so our programming
has evolved but we've learned how to
kind of maximize results by doing each
main lift twice a week all right but
it's really hard to squat twice a week
deadlift twice a week hip thrust twice a
week bench twice a week military twice a
week chin up twice a week so we
typically do one day of you know the
traditional variation the standard
variation and then one day of a
different variation and a lot of times
it's a lockout variation when when i say
lockout it could be a pause or it could
be uh like using accommodating
resistance in the form of bands or
chains you see one of the most respected
strength coaches in the world is louis
simmons from west side barbell club and
he really popularized the use of
accommodate resistance and the
literature is known as variable
resistance but it's basically using
bands and chains for example so we've
been using accommodating resistance on
all six lifts yes we'll even do chain
chin ups or band resisted not band
assisted chinos band resisted chin ups
bar plus band military press using
accommodating resistance with bench
press and hip thrust is easy you know
there's so many different ways but we've
found ways to increase the range of
motion decrease the range of motion
changing grip with changing stance with
using different implements we've
developed a full on system maximizing
your strength and like i said earlier i
believe that strong lifting uh is the
best way to maximize your physique you
know yes you're gonna do your lateral
raises we do upper body abduction with
lateral raises to work the lateral delts
but we also do hip abduction to maximize
the upper glute growth and we throw in
accessories you're gonna do curls you're
gonna do some rows you're gonna do some
leg curls and things like that those
help both with function and muscularity
but the focus is always on building your
six lifts and your total and we look at
both absolute strength and relative
strength so both are both are very
important so the meats are so much fun
there's over 40 medals we give out at
the end of the competition so there's
all these different ways to win a medal
with all the different lifts and then we
have the strongest upper body the
strongest lower body the strongest
pusher and the strongest puller these
make it fun for the competitors
sometimes you'll announce the winner and
you'll see the person be so shocked like
oh my god i want a medal which brings me
to my next point the benefits of strong
lifting i've already discussed as a
lifter you know you're going to improve
your strength your physique your
confidence but if you're a trainer or
like a gym owner or a coach of a lot of
different lifters you should start doing
strong lifting training because it's
going to fast forward your success as a
trainer coach you see i have the
strongest all-natural female gym in the
world i didn't put out an ad and say hey
i'm looking for the strongest girls in
san diego come to glute lab no these
were just normal women wanting to build
their glutes they didn't come to me
exceptionally strong they became strong
as hell through strong lifting only one
of the squad members had ever done a
powerlifting meet and that was ashley
hodge and as i showed you earlier ashley
hodges physique made a complete change
via strong lifting but i have just
recently created a certification for
those people who are interested in
learning all about strongly if you found
this video interesting then you should
check out the cert you know it's 300
bucks and it's so comprehensive you know
my partner glenn cordoza he and i wrote
glute lab together we've been working on
this for an entire year one full year so
if you're familiar with our book glute
lab you know how comprehensive it is
when we were equally as comprehensive
with our strong lifting cert we've
detailed every program that we've done
along the way and how the training
changed from meat to meat you know so we
have training for miami training for
tulum the training for san diego the
training for la the program's always
morphed a little bit and we explain the
rationale we also have separate programs
we created depending on the scenario we
have the base program which is the
allegra pr program which is legendary
glenn my co-author he's not even a
trainer he's a writer he went and taught
a couple of his buddies the allegro pr
plan and they're killing it he realizes
he could be a very successful trainer
because of this allegra pr plan he's
more enthusiastic about strong lifting
than anyone i recently started training
ashton my client he's an 18 year old kid
but when i started training he was 17
and in just four months he's now dead
lifting 650 he's squatting 585 he's all
natural i mean but you know given the
fact he's 18 i'm curious what his t
levels are at they're probably at 1200
anyway the kid never gets sore
nevertheless he does the allegra pr plan
and his strength has skyrocketed i'm
really curious to see how strong he'll
be in a couple of years when i was
coming up as a trainer i would have
killed to have an exact blueprint of how
the strongest gym went about their
business how they the exact programs
they used to develop this world-class
elite levels of strength and that's what
i've done i've taken the guesswork out
of it and given you the exact formula
that i used with my glute squad so what
does the future hold for strong lifting
well i need to take it from like it's a
one-man show right now me uh you know i
i'm always at the meets and i'm the the
judge and the spotter and the motivator
and the
the coach and the organizer i need it to
become popular around the world i need
more people getting certified and i need
i want the sport to grow i think it's a
better strength sport than all of those
maybe one day it could get equally or
more popular than powerlifting or
olympic weightlifting or strongman or
crossfit i love all of those systems but
for physique training strong lifting is
the best so i think it should be the
most popular in time but that's going to
take a lot of time to get there and i
need a lot of people to buy in and
participate so when you do these six
lifts in the fashion i've described when
you train for the competition you're
gonna get muscular those strength gains
equal muscularity gains and if you stay
the same weight and you gain muscle that
means you lose fat so strong lifting can
help you bulk up if you're eating more
it can help you recomp if you're eating
the same and improve your body
composition or it can help you when
you're cutting by causing you to keep
your muscle and lose fat for weight loss
now kind of this elusive feat in strong
lifting is the 12 times body weight
total and right now ashley hodge is the
only one to have hit that but you can
calculate yours right now but keep in
mind the rules you know a lot of times
you ask someone how much do you bench
and they tell you what their bench is
when they bounce it off their chest and
lift their butt off the bench that's not
a real bench press or they tell you what
they can squat and then you look at
their squat and they don't even make it
close to parallel they're talking about
a quarter squat or half squat given the
rules of strong lifting you can estimate
what your total would be by just adding
up what is your max squat bench press
deadlift military press chin up and hip
thrust add those all up and then divide
it by your body weight like i consider
myself a strong guy i'm at like 10.5 you
know getting to 12 is amazing so that's
a good goal for those of you competitive
people out there one day going for the
12 times bodyweight strong lifting total
now i made a post on instagram in
january of 2021 this was like a month
after tulum and it was the average
strength levels with my competitors so
it involved like 20 of my clients at the
time their average body weight was 142
pounds okay the average squat was 238
pounds the average bench press was 135.
the average deadlift was 293 pounds the
average military press 91 pounds the
average chin up was 181 pounds and the
chin up you get by adding up your body
weight plus the extra load so that was
like body weight plus 39 extra pounds
and then the average hip thrust was 542.
the average glute squad member could hit
those almost 550 pounds and the average
total was 14.80 so that's the six lifts
added together now that was 11 months
ago a lot of my squad members have
gotten a lot stronger since then so as
you can see these methods work another
thing i'd like to see in the future is
to add males into the mix you know i've
only had all female competitions so far
and i want males to be able to compete
in strong lifting as well it's just a
little more daunting you know there's a
lot more plates involved with the
strongest men out there and you know so
i need more spotters and better
equipment now you know all about strong
lifting i hope i answered all your
questions and satisfied your curiosity
again if you want more check out this
certification i think it'll be fun to
see people in their in their bios
writing like strong lifting certified i
tell my squad members you know get
strong engine sort of it adds a feather
to your cap you know you have one more
skill set you can help train clients who
are interested in competing in strong
lifting and most of all for the fellow
trainers and coaches out there i would
love for you to experience what i have
with my squad you know it brings
everyone together you develop serious
camaraderie and you know when you go
travel as a group and conduct these
meets especially if you travel to
different cities to compete you develop
these lasting memories and you get
really close with your team and you know
it's hard in this world to find
like-minded people i can't tell you how
much happiness and satisfaction it's
brought to my own life and i would love
for other people to partake in that as
well all right so that's a wrap i hope i
answered all your questions i hope i
satisfied your curiosity now you know
all about strong hunting definitely
check out the cert if you're interested
if you like the video definitely give it
a thumbs up if you have questions that i
didn't answer be sure to ask them in the
comments and always of course make sure
you're subscribed to my channel i'm
gonna keep pumping out content every
week i've even started doing shorts
lately which are focused on you know
little tips for glute building or
technique corrections and i'm sure
you'll enjoy them alright that's a wrap
thank you for watching my video and i
hope to see you one day on the strong
lifting platform
you